<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8' ?>
<!--
  ~ Copyright 2011 JBoss Inc
  ~
  ~ Licensed under the Apache License, Version 2.0 (the "License");
  ~ you may not use this file except in compliance with the License.
  ~ You may obtain a copy of the License at
  ~
  ~       http://www.apache.org/licenses/LICENSE-2.0
  ~
  ~ Unless required by applicable law or agreed to in writing, software
  ~ distributed under the License is distributed on an "AS IS" BASIS,
  ~ WITHOUT WARRANTIES OR CONDITIONS OF ANY KIND, either express or implied.
  ~ See the License for the specific language governing permissions and
  ~ limitations under the License.
  -->

<chapter version="5.0"
         xsi:schemaLocation="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook http://www.docbook.org/xml/5.0/xsd/docbook.xsd http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink http://www.docbook.org/xml/5.0/xsd/xlink.xsd"
         xml:base="./" xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
         xmlns:xs="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
         xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" xmlns:ns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook">
    <title>Drools MAS - Architectural Overview </title>
    <section>
        <title>Architecture Introduction</title>
    
        <para> Each individual agent is composed by a set of components that provides different set of functionalities.
            The following section describe these internal components and their main responsabilities.

        </para>
        <mediaobject>
            <imageobject>
                <imagedata fileref="images/01-agent-high-level-arch.png" format="PNG"/>
            </imageobject>
        </mediaobject>
        <para>
            As you can see an individual agent is composed by three main components. The Core module, the Agent Communication Language module and 
            an Utility module. Domain specific artifacts will usually be attached to the agent structure to solve domain specific problems and 
            situations.
        </para>
       
        <para>
            The Core module is reposible to host the internal mechanisms that the agent will use to react and expose an endpoint that will enable us to 
            interact with it. How the agent internal structure will look like will be defined based on the configurations that we 
        </para>    
       
        <para>
            The ACL module provides the Agent Communication Language Structures. This language is composed by 22 performatives that will 
            enable the interactions between different agents. This ACL is based on FIPA-ACL, and right now there is a one to one mapping with the 
            FIPA-ACL standard. 
        </para>
       
        <para>
            The Util module contains a set of helper classes that will be used to speed up and simplify the development process. Message Factories, 
            Decoders/Encoders and general tools will be provided by this module.
        </para>
       
        <para>
            Each of these three modules are represented by JAR packages in Java. That can be added as dependencies to your project using the following 
            Maven artifacts:
            <itemizedlist>
                <listitem>groupId - org.drools.mas</listitem>
                <listitem>artifactId - drools-mas-core</listitem>
            </itemizedlist>
            
            <itemizedlist>
                <listitem>groupId - org.drools.mas</listitem>
                <listitem>artifactId - drools-mas-acl</listitem>
            </itemizedlist>   
            <itemizedlist>
                <listitem>groupId - org.drools.mas</listitem>
                <listitem>artifactId - drools-mas-util</listitem>
            </itemizedlist>       

        </para>
       
        <para>
            The following section goes deep in each of these components and analyze the simple Emergency Agent example.
        </para>
    </section>
    
    

</chapter>
